A Guide to the Papers of the Buxton, Lea & Marshall Families ca. 1855-1965
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Buxton, Lea & Marshall Families ca. 1855-1965
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11412
22 Hollinger boxes and one oversize box, ca. 9 linear shelf feet
Papers of the Buxton, Lea, and Marshall families of Pennsylvania and Virginia, ca. 3,000 items, include personal and business correspondence, diaries, journals, ledgers, notebooks and guest books, photographs and photograph albums, postcards, newspaper clippings and portraits. The correspondence is primarily that of Dr. Harry Taylor Marshall (1875-1929) and Nancy Lea Marshall of Albemarle County, Virginia, Joseph Tatnall Lea (1840-1916) of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, the Cabeen family of Germantown [Philadelphia], Pennsylvania, and the Buxton family of Newport News, Virginia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the University of Virginia Library in honor of William D. Buxton, M.D. and Pauline Marshall Buxton, by Lucinda Martin, Charlottesville, Virginia, William Buxton, Free Union, Virginia, Susan Spencer, Wyndmoor, Pennsylvania, and Nancy Silverman, Newtown Square, Pennsylvania, on June 19, 1998.
Biographical/Historical Information
The earliest material in this collection pertains to the Cabeen family, chiefly the letters of Annie Anderson (Cabeen) Lea (1842-1921), daughter of Emma (Anderson) Cabeen and Robert B. Cabeen, an iron commission merchant of Philadelphia and a former president of the Philadelphia & Reading Railway Company. Annie Cabeen's brothers and sisters include: Frank Cabeen, Ellen Roberta Cabeen (1859-1936), and Louise Wakeman Cabeen (1858-1916). The letters are between Annie and her family, and Annie and her future husband, Joseph Tatnall Lea, whom she married on December 6, 1865, at Germantown, Pennsylvania.
Joseph Tatnall Lea was the son of Mary Mickle (Matlock) Lea and Robeson Lea (son of Joseph and Sarah Ann Robeson Lea), a grain merchant of Philadelphia. Joseph Lea attended Thomas Baldwin's private school in Philadelphia and the Lawrenceville School in New Jersey. According to the National Cyclopedia of American Biography (Vol. 17, p. 103), in 1857, Lea entered his uncle's firm, Hacker, Lea and Company, a dry goods commission house of Philadelphia. Two years later, working with another uncle, Joseph Lea, he was sent to Baltimore, Maryland, to open a branch house of a similar business but was interrupted by the outbreak of the Civil War.
Lea originally enlisted in the 114th Pennsylvania reserves, and was promoted to lieutenant and adjutant, serving on the staff of General Phillip R. de Trobriand who commanded a division of the 3rd Corps, Army of the Potomac. He was wounded at the battle of Chancellorsville. Leaving the army in January of 1864, Joseph Lea opened a branch house of the family firm in New York City under the name of J.T. Lea & Company.
Eight years later he returned to Philadelphia, and in 1875 became interested in coal mining operations in West Virginia. On the death of his father-in-law, he succeeded him in the coal and iron commission business in Philadelphia under the name of Cabeen and Company (later J. Tatnall Lea and Company). From 1904-1915, he was president of the First National Bank of Philadelphia, and also had interests in the Lake Superior Corporation, the Pennsylvania Fire Insurance Company, and the Pennsylvania Salt Company.
The children born to Annie and Joseph Tatnall Lea (1840-1916) include: Ellen Roberta Lea (b. 1866), Florence Lea Fletcher (1868-1911), Langdon Lea who married Belknap Lyons, Mrs. William H. Nicholson, Jr. (Katharine Leonard Lea), and Mrs. Harry T. Marshall (Nancy Lea). Nancy Lea and Dr. Harry Taylor Marshall (1875-1929), married at "Bloomfield," Ivy, Virginia, the summer home of the Lea family since 1875, on June 17, 1911. Harry Taylor Marshall, son of Charles and Rebecca (Snowden) Marshall, graduated from Johns Hopkins University (1894 A.B. and 1898 M.D.) and interned at the Johns Hopkins Hospital, joining its faculty as a fellow in pathology1899-1900, an assistant in pathology 1900-1903, an instructor in medicine, 1903-1905, and pediatrics, 1905-1906. According to the National Cyclopedia of American Biography (Vol. 34, p. 104), Marshall also worked summers as a recorder for the U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey (1892-1894); interned at the Thomas Wilson Sanitarium (1898 & 1903); was a travelling fellow for the Rockefeller Institute (1901-1902), when he studied under Professor Ehrlich in Frankfort, Germany.
In 1906, Marshall moved to the Philippine Islands, where he was pathologist at the Bureau of Science and Professor of Pathology at the College of Medicine, Manila. He returned to the United States in 1908 to become the Walter Reed Professor of Pathology at the University of Virginia until his death in 1929. The children of Nancy Lea and Dr. Harry Taylor Marshall were Marion Pauline Marshall Buxton, (married William Dimmock Buxton), Harry Taylor Marshall, Katherine Marshall, Nancy Lea ([1915?]- ) who married Thomas Valentine Cooper in 1943, and Snowden Marshall (1912- ).
Scope and Content Information
Scope and Content Information
Papers of the Buxton, Lea, and Marshall families of Pennsylvania and Virginia, ca. 3,000 items (22 Hollinger boxes and one oversize box, ca. 9 linear shelf feet), ca. 1855-1965, include personal and business correspondence, diaries, journals, ledgers, notebooks and guest books, photographs and photograph albums, postcards, newspaper clippings and portraits. The correspondence is primarily that of Dr. Harry Taylor Marshall (1875-1929) and Nancy Lea Marshall of Albemarle County, Virginia, Joseph Tatnall Lea (1840-1916) of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, the Cabeen family of Germantown [Philadelphia], Pennsylvania, and the Buxton family of Newport News, Virginia.
The early correspondence of the Cabeen family, March 28-May 9, 1859, chiefly consists of letters between Annie Cabeen and her family, while she is away on a tour of the southern states of South Carolina, Georgia, Tennessee and Florida, with friends of the family. She describes the flora and fauna of the area, the hotels, her activities, the people she meets, riding the stage coach, her visit to the oldest house in the United States and the old fort in St. Augustine, Florida, which held Osceola during the Seminole wars, a visit to a coquina quarry in Florida, and her visit to the Mammoth Cave and White's Cave in Kentucky.
Other topics in the Cabeen family correspondence include a discussion about the beginning of the Civil War, especially concerning Baltimore, Maryland (1861 April 21); and balloon flight and the concept of "aerostatic artillery" (1862 April 26). The courtship correspondence between Annie Cabeen and her future husband, Joseph Tatnall Lea, begins with a letter from Lea, at Camp with Union General [Nathaniel Prentiss] Banks, Washington, D.C., written September 1, 1862. Lea began his Civil War service as an officer in Company "F" 114th Regiment of the Pennsylvania Volunteers.
Civil War Correspondence in 1862
Lea mentions the desertion of some of the men because of the non-payment of bounties upon their arrival in Washington, D.C. (1862 September 9 & 25); another letter mentions two other officers, Captain Frank A. Eliot and Charles A. Robinson, adjutant of the regiment, listening to the Germantown Cornet Band, and the flag of the "Zouaves d' Afrique" before the door of his tent (1862 September 21, Arlington Heights, Virginia).
On October 7, 1862, Lea is at Hunter's Chapel, Virginia, and talks about distributing medicine; a letter dated October 19, finds Lea at Poolesville, Maryland, and contains his proposal of marriage to Annie Cabeen, rejected at that time; and on November 14, he writes from near Waterloo, Virginia, disturbed at the removal of General George McClellan as head of the Northern army, "it is rather hard that the wishes of stay at home abolitionists should be consulted in preference to those who are bearing the hardships and making the sacrifice." A final letter for 1862, written from Camp Pitcher, near Falmouth, Virginia, describes his quarters and the hardships endured by the men because of the weather (December 9).
Civil War Correspondence in 1863
While at Camp Pitcher, Lea mentions the capture of the Germantown Cornet Band by the Southern forces and refers to a fierce battle [Battle of Fredericksburg?] but gives no details (January 15); near Potomac Creek, he writes about the abolitionists and reports on a wedding in Washington, D.C. complete with fireworks that cost two thousand dollars (March 15) and assures Annie of his lack of sympathy for "Copperheads" and "Democrats" and his changed opinion of "colored regiments" (April 28). On May 18, he is at home on leave because of his arm, having been wounded in the battle of Chancellorsville, and on July 16, he sends her his new address, Headquarters, 1st Division, 3rd Corps, Army of the Potomac, as he plans to rejoin his comrades.
Letters from Joseph Tatnall Lea assure Annie that he has arranged his business affairs so that upon his return from the war he will be the head of the family's New York house, and will be able to marry her; apparently they came to an understanding before he left home; General George Meade has crossed the Potomac River after Robert E. Lee, and Lea hopes to rejoin his fellow soldiers by accompanying the mail carrier of the 3rd Division of his Corps (July 19-20). Lea was home on leave in Philadelphia, having escaped from Staunton, Virginia (August 17) but returned to Washington on August 25.
His new position, which he assumed at Sulphur Springs, Virginia, was that of Aid to the Headquarters, 3rd Brigade, 1st Division, 3rd Corps, Army of the Potomac, commanded by Colonel [Regis, Denis de Keredem, Comte] de Trobriand. Lea hopes to soon fill a vacancy with Fitzhugh Birney; and mentions that the battle of Chancellorsville reduced his brigade from about two thousand to eight hundred men (August 26-30). While still at Sulphur Springs, Lea mentions his disgust with Lt. Colonel Merrill of the 17th Maine, who "has a great dread of being put upon an equality with Negroes" (September 4); refers to his participation in the battle of Chancellorsville where he broke his arm (September 5); says the 3rd Corps now commanded by General [William Henry] French (1863 September 7); and discusses one woman's attitude to patriotic duty (1863 September 10).
Stationed near Culpeper, Virginia, Lea mentions John Minor Botts (1802-1869), "a [former] prisoner paroled by the Rebel government" (1863 September 17); the return of two regiments to the Brigade who had been in New York enforcing the draft, bringing the Brigade up to 1,500 men, with his whole division with sixteen regiments containing about 4,000 men (1863 September 19); mentions the news of the setback General William Starke Rosecrans suffered at the battle of Chickamauga (1863 September 23); Lea discusses the effects of conscription on the quality of the Northern army (1863 September 24); his dislike of Colonel Charles Henry Tucky Collis, a Philadelphia attorney who organized both the independent company of Zouaves d' Afrique and the 114th Pennsylvania Volunteers; the attempt of Collis to arrange to get Lea's regiment transferred from the 3rd Brigade into General John C. Robinson's Second Division of the First Corps; his contempt for Collis as a commander, who he considered his social inferior; and the earlier deaths of his two friends, Joe Chandler and Frank Eliot, while serving under Collis at battle of Chancellorsville (September 25, 27 & 28); and the receipt of new instruments for the band as a gift of General [David Bell] Birney (1863 September 26).
Topics raised in the letters of October 1863 include the Third Army Corps Union (October 2); a march to Sulphur Springs to prevent the Rebels from outflanking them, crossing the Hazel and Hedgmon Rivers, and mention of a cavalry battle near Brandy Station (October 10-12). By October 14th, they were occupying an almost impregnable position between the old Bull Run Battleground and Centerville, with heavy fighting at Bristoe Station involving the 2nd and 5th Corps and two brigades of his Corps, but from another Division. Both Lea's Brigade and the First (Collis') had a sharp engagement at Auburn the afternoon of October 13, which he describes (October 14). While at Fairfax Station, Lea describes the reaction of the Corps to the appearance of General Daniel Edgar Sickles (1825-1914) on the road (October 15), and the execution of a deserter from his Brigade (October 16). On October 19th, they marched to Bristoe Station.
On October 21st, after marching to Catlett's Station, supposedly to rebuild the railroad, Lea voices his criticism of General Meade "we are all deeply mortified at our recent movements. Lee with about ten thousand men, as it now turns out, forced us to retire almost to Washington then totally destroyed the railroad, and has quietly gone back again to his old quarters." Still at Catlett's Station, he complains about General Meade's orders sending all the sutlers back to Washington, who were apparently captured by John Singleton Mosby on the way, because now the forces could not buy any good tobacco or cigars (October 25); and describes his idea of the role of the wife in the home (October 26). After marching to Cedar Run, their headquarters was set up at "Pilgrim's Rest," a house owned by Union people, part of the "Jersey settlement" of about fifty families who emigrated from New Jersey to Virginia about a decade before and who had lost all of their livestock to marauders, "I am really ashamed of the way our men have behaved around here, in some cases entering pantries guarded by women, and helping themselves to anything they could find. We have had to put safeguards around at all the houses to protect the women from insult" (October 27). The headquarters moved from "Pilgrim's Rest" to Warrenton Junction but the brigade did not go into winter quarters yet (October 30). Lea is angry with his African-American servant because of his carelessness with his horse (November 5).
Lea's letters are full of details about the action at Kelly's Ford, where Lea's brigade drove away the enemy, capturing nearly two Confederate regiments, about five hundred prisoners, and mentioning General David Bell Birney's narrow escape from a Confederate shell (November 7 & 9). They now occupy the winter quarters of Richard Stoddert Ewell's Corps, which was captured during the recent fight, of which he furnishes additional details, explaining the chance death of Captain Maynard on the staff of the First Brigade, killed by a stray bullet from a skirmish some distance away, and mentions that part of his brigade is camped on the estate of John Minor Botts (November 10).
Other topics in November include the order for the men from his brigade to rebuild the fence destroyed by the Confederates on the John Minor Botts estate, who also suffered the loss of his pigs to hungry Union forces nearby (November 11); an order to stop building winter quarters, and mention of General Meade's General Orders complimenting the 3rd Brigade on their actions at Kelly's Ford (November 12-13); hearing cannon fire at Kelly's Ford, and comments about the lack of good chaplains in the Northern Army (November 15); an exhibition of the Corps to a few British officers (November 16); rumors of a big campaign towards Lynchburg (November 18); the homesickness of his servant Adolphus and a mention that the Lea family business sales now are at the rate of one million per annum (November 19); and notes that three more deserters from his Corps will be shot in a few days (November 21).
Lea writes that Collis has again made application to General Birney to have Lea returned to his regiment which Birney did not approve; He has heard a rumor that Collis plans to appeal Birney's decision to General French, the Corps commander. He also notes that an order, issued before the Kelly's Ford battle, has come from the War Department, mustering Colonel de Trobriand out of the service, to be replaced by Colonel [Thomas Washington] Egan (November 22). Although preparations for a troop movement began on November 22, the rainy weather has prevented any action. Lea is disgusted that the Washington newspapers forecast their move twenty-four hours in advance, indicating they were crossing the Rapidan River at Germanna Ford (November 24).
After a hiatus in correspondence, Lea writes about being engaged in a severe fight at a place called Morris' Farm, where his division lost 264 men (174 in one brigade); Lea was hit in the shoulder by a spent ball when Egan had sent him to move forward the 17th Maine to occupy the front line during the hottest part of the battle; Lea's brigade was the rear guard of the 3rd Corps; he discusses the argument between French and Meade at Birney's headquarters, where French acccused Meade of taking two thirds of his command from him and giving them to a boy (Warren), who then did nothing; they lost one field officer and six line officers during the engagement [the Mine Run Campaign?], and says "the 3rd Division got scared and fell back with very few killed or wounded, and our brigade was put in to stop the Rebels, which we did, never yielding an inch" (December 3-4).
Lea notes that he is busy writing the official record of the part taken by his brigade in the late troop movement (December 6); recalls participating in the battle at Fredericksburg last winter and the famous "mud march" (December 8); comments concerning General French; describes the efforts of his uncle Joseph and T.D. Eliot to secure his discharge from the army on account of the family business by a visit to the home of Secretary of War, Edwin M. Stanton (December 12); refers to the stories about the Kelly's Ford fight as described in the New York Illustrated Papers and Harper's Weekly& Illustrated News; the presence in Colonel Egan's Regiment, of a former head cook at the New York Hotel, a French man, who was detailed for special duty as a cook for Headquarters and who prepared all sorts of French dishes (December 13); and Lea's receipt of the news that Stanton had agreed to receive Lea's resignation as soon as it was forwarded with the approval of the Brigade commander, but a mix-up caused a delay in the document reaching Stanton (December 13, 29-30).
Civil War Correspondence in 1864
Lea learns that General Birney has ordered him to report back to his original regiment, which had been taken out of the Division and put on guard duty at General Meade's Headquarters; Birney also had disapproved his resignation from the army (1864 January 1); Lea hopes to rejoin his regiment as an adjutant and plans to reapply to resign from the army; his address would be 114th Pennsylvania Volunteers, Headquarters, Army of the Potomac (January 2); mentions his dislike of Colonel West and that his twenty-fourth birthday is on January 7th (January 4); gives his opinion of Botts, whose complaints concerning the troops cutting down his trees for fire wood has caused them to have to move their camp (January 6); Lea still struggling to get his discharge papers to Stanton (January 8); they have moved their headquarters to another home two miles from Brandy Station (January 10); Lea discusses being made the manager of his brigade for the Third Corps Ball given for the officers (January 18, 24, & 26); Lea has finally received word of action on his resignation from the army (January 28); and Lea's resignation has been approved and he is in Washington, D.C., on the way home to Philadelphia (February 3).
Joseph Tatnall Lea and Annie Cabeen continue to write their courtship letters until their marriage on December 6, 1865, while Lea resides in New York City and works at the "rag trade," actually a dry goods commission house, for his Uncle Joseph Lea, and Annie Cabeen lives with her family in Germantown, a residential section of Philadelphia (1864 February 10). Other topics include a subscription to the Mercantile Library (March 10); the family of Mrs. Ward split by the Civil War (1864 March 31); a business sale to Alexander Turney Stewart, owner of a dry goods retail store in New York (1864 April 12); a reference to a "collapse on Wall Street" and its effect upon some businessmen (1864 April 19); and mention of "little retail stores kept by women" in Philadelphia (1864 May 6).
After a visit with General de Trobriand, who had orders to assume command of New York City and the harbor, Lea hears news of the death of General Alexander Hays at the battle of the Wilderness in Virginia; agrees to be a "volunteer aid" for de Trobriand to help put down any riots like those of the summer of 1863; and learns of the death of General James Clay Rice (1864 May 8, 10, 11); Lea hears of more casualties from his former comrades in the battle of the Wilderness and hopes for success under Grant (May 19); shares news of his old regiment from Ned Bowen (June 9); and learns of the death of his friend, Fitz Birney, from disease (June 20).
Lea refers to the sinking of the Rebel privateer Alabama(July 7); concern over Jubal Early's raid on Washington and Maryland, the price of gold, and the economy (July 10-14); ideas on marriage (July 19 and 1865 August 21); opinions on the income tax, the restoration of the Union, Abraham Lincoln, and the death of Mrs. Kate Ward's nephew during the Ft. Pillow "Massacre" (July 21); the hopeful news from the battle of Mobile Bay and Atlanta, and concern over the Presidential election in the fall (August 9); Lea's ten day business trip to New England (1864 September 4-11); warning for Annie not to visit New York City in November on election day, as there may be violence and trouble (September 25); and mentions the capture of Savannah, Georgia (December 14). In one of the few letters to Annie Cabeen not from Lea, D.P. Heap, Engineer Camp, near Petersburg, Virginia, writes about the celebration over the capture of Atlanta and the earthworks around Petersburg (1864 September 4).
Civil War Correspondence in 1865
Lea goes on a business trip early in the year to textile mills in Massachusetts and Rhode Island (January 11-16); writes concerning his earlier capture and escape from the Rebel forces, brought to mind by meeting a fellow prisoner, John M. Sawhill (January 29); mentions friends attending the Purim Ball, an annual Jewish masquerade given at the Academy, remarking that he sells a large part of the store's goods to the Jews in New York (March 14); the premature report of Robert E. Lee's surrender to Ulysses S. Grant (April 7); with news of immediate peace, Lea hopes they can now be married in October and reports on his jury duty (April 11); discusses the effects of the death of Abraham Lincoln and the ending of the war (April 17, both letters, and 19, 20, & 22); and describes a visit to the site of the former Fort Washington, on upper Manhattan Island, on the Hudson River (April 20).